Finding Aid for the Sami Assaad Aintabi Collection of Arabic Manuscripts LSC.0833
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sami Assaad Aintabi collection of Arabic manuscripts
circa 1200-1851
UCLA Library Special Collections
Aintabi, Sami Assaad
LSC.0833
1 unknown (1 oversize box)
10 Linear Feet (20 boxes)
Restrictions on Access
Portions of collection unprocessed. Material in the collection is unavailable for access. Please contact Special Collections reference (spec-coll@library.ucla.edu) for more information.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303023606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of Islamic manuscripts relating to a variety of subjects.
manuscripts (documents) -- Arab countries.; Aintabi, Sami Assaad
- Kafi n-nabin fi tahrir at-tanbih, 848 H. (?).; 2; No pagination. 23 lines.; 28 cm. (Box 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-hadi lilhaqq 'ala minhaj as-sirat al-mustaqim."
  Scribe: Ali Ahmad al-'Asif.
  General note
  Ref: GAL S I 670(?).
- al-Targhib wat-tarhib, 856 H.; 3[?]; No pagination. 21 lines.; 26.5 cm. (Box 2)
  Incipit: "Sala ash-shaikh al-imam al-hafiz al- 'allama Zakiy ad-Din 'Abd al- 'Azim... al-Mundhiri."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Muhammad ibn Muhammad al-Khatib (known as Ibn al-Zakzuk and Muhammad ibn Uthman ibn Ali).
  Ref: GAL I 367 S I 627.
- Asas al-balagha (?), 1015 H.; 4; No pagination. 33 lines.; 28.5 cm. (Box 2)
  Incipit: first page torn.
  Ref: GAL I 292, S I 511, 553.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 4/64[?]; 10 leaves. (47-56). 18 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 2)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al- 'alamin wa-la hawla wa-la quwwata illa li' llah."
- Kitab al-tenwir fi isqat at-tadbir, n.d.; 5; No pagination. 28 lines.; 26 cm. (Box 3)
  Incipit: "Qala 'l-shaikh al-imam al- 'alim al-allama ..."
  Manuscript incomplete at the end.
  Ref: GAL II 118, S II 165.
- Saqt az-zand, 1157 H.; 6; No pagination. 26-28 lines.; 32 cm. (Box 3)
  Incipit: "In kunta mudda 'iyan mawaddata Zaynab..."
  Scribe: Ishaq Yusuf.
  Ref: GAL I 254, S I 542.
- Sharh al-fiqh al-akbar, 953 H.; 7/1; No pagination. 20 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 4)
  Incipit: "Hadha sharh al-kitab (sic) al-figh al-akbar alladhi sannafahu al-imam al- azim Abu Hanifa."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Jamal al-Din.
  Ref: GAL I 170. S I 285.
- al-Nahr al-madd mina l-bahr (ath-thulth al-awwal), n.d.; 8; No pagination. 23 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 4)
  Incipit: "Qala al-shaikh al-imam al- alim al-allama ... Athiraddin Abu Hayyan Muhammad ibn Yusuf ibn Ali ibn Yusuf ibn Hayyan al-Andalusi."
  Ref: GAL S II 135-136.
- Zahr al-kimam (akmam), n.d.; 9; No pagination. 15 lines.; 28 cm. (Box 5)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al-alamin ... wa-salat (bhu) ala sayyidina Muhammad alladhi arsalahu lin-nas kaffatan bashiran aw nadhira."
  Bulky volume.
  Ref: GAL II 265 S II 378.
  For author's name see GAL S II 377.
- Kitab majma' al-bahrain wa-multaqa an- naiyirain (vol.3), 831 H.; 10; No pagination. 21 lines.; 26 cm. (Box 5)
  Incipit: "Kitab al- jinayat."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Musa ibn 'Umran al-Ghazzi al-mufti al-Hanafi.
  Ref: GAL S I 658.
- Sharh al- uyun fi sharh risalat Ibn Zaidun, 1066 H.; 11; No pagination. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 5)
  Incipit: "Qala ash-shaikh al-imam al-' alim al-'allama ... Muhammad ibn Nubata."
  Ref: GAL II 12.
- (Kitab) al-ashbah wan-naza ir, 1071 H.; 12; 221 leaves. 23 lines.; 23 cm. (Box 5)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah wa-salam 'ala 'ibadihi."
  Ref: GAL S II 425.
- Tariq al-huda wa-muzin ar-rada, n.d.; 13; 188 leaves. 23 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 6)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi afada ala hada iq haqa' iq al-mukhlisin sha'abib al-hidaya."
  The Manuscript is incomplete.
  Some parts are missing at the end which are supplemented by Muhammad As ad ibn Muhammad Naji al-Aintabi (collector) in 1340 H. from a Manuscript dated 1089.
  Ref: GAL II 292.
- Kitab awarif al-ma arif, 619 H.(?).; 14; 273 leaves. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 6)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al- azim sha' nuhu al-qawiy sultanuhu."
  Ref: GAL I 440.
- 989 H., 15; 255 leaves. 22 lines.; 26 cm. (Box 6)
  Incipit: "Qala as-Suudi huwa ism Allah al- A 'zam."
  Scribe: Ibrahim ibn Wariyya (Warid?).
- Risala fi l-awqaf al-lazima, 1177 H.; 15; 4 leaves. 30 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 6)
  Incipit: "Ta 'lil al-waqf al-lazim."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad ibn al-Hajj 'Abdalhayy ibn al-Hajj 'Abdallah.
- al-Arba 'un fi usul ad-din, n.d.; No pagination. 19 lines.; 18.5 cm. (Box 17)
  Incipit: "Kitab al-arba 'in fi usual ad-din wa-fihi al-qism ath-thalith min aqsam kitab al-jawahir wa-huwa qism al-lawahiq."
  The last page of the Manuscript is missing.
  It is supplemented by a copy from the printed edition of Farah-Allah Dhaki al-Kurdi (1328 H.).
  Ref: GAL I 421. GAL S I 746.
- al-Juz' ath-thalith min tafsir al-qur' an (an-nukat wal- 'uyun) (vol.3), n.d.; 17; No pagination. 17 lines.; 24.5 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Qauluhu 'azza wa-jalla thumma badalna makan as-sayyi'a al-hasana."
  Ref: GAL I 386 SI 668.
- Is'af al-qasid li-tafahhum masa'il Shihab az-zahid, 1106 H.; 17; No pagination. 15 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi najana min mabahith al-'ulum al-rasmiyya."
  Scribe: Ibrahim ibn al-'Hajj Muhammad.
  Ref: GAL S II 112, 195,274.
- al-Qawl al-badl' fi-s-salat ala l-habib ash-shafi, 860 H.; 17; No pagination. 21 lines.; 17 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Qala sh-shaikh al-imam al-habr al humam ..."
  Ref: GAL S II 32.
- 'Umdat ahl at-tawfiq wat-tasdid, 1023 H.; 18; No pagination. 21 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Qala ash-shaikh al-imam Abu Abdallah Muhammad ibn Yusuf as-Sanusi
  Scribe: 'Uthman ibn Mustafa.
  Ref: GAL II 250 S II 353.
- Kitab al-majmu, 1056 H.; 19/1; No pagination. 18 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Kitab at-tahara akhbarana al-qadi al-ajall."
  Scribe: Ahmad ibn Nasr ibn Muhammad.
  Ref: GAL S I 313.
- Kitab an-nasikh wal-mansukh, 1061 H.; 19/2; No pagination. 19 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Yaqulu 'l- abd al-faqir ila rahmat Allah ta ala Ibrahim ibn Muhammd ibn Abdalla ..."
  Ref: GAL S II 985, 25.
- Riyad ar-rabi' fi 'ilm al-ma ani wal-bayan wal-badi', 1232 H.; 19/3; No pagination. 20 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi allama al-insan al-bayan."
  Ref: GAL S II 817,915.
- Fatawi (al-fatawi al-Tirimtashiya fi l-waqa i al-Shazziya), 1120 H.; 20; 152 leaves. 25 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "Hamdan liman an' ama 'alaina bi-'ilm ash-shara i wal-ahkam."
  Scribe: Ibn Zaitun.
  Ref: GAL II 312 S II 429 (Fatawi at- Tirimtashi).
- [No further description available], n.d.; 21; No pagination. 13 lines.; 19 cm. (Box 7)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi zayyana qulub al-muridin bi-nur ma'rifatihi."
  First volume only.
  --- -----. Another copy.
  1 reel 35mm negative microfilm.
- Ismat al-unbiya, n.d.; 22/1; No pagination. 21 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 8)
  Ref: GAL I 507.
- Nafis al-riad li-i 'dam al-amrad, n.d.; 22/2; No pagination. 25 lines.; 19 cm. (Box 8)
  Scribe: Abd al-Ghari ibn Molla Ali known as al-Kadalajiy (?).
  Ref: GAL SN I 764 (?).
- Bidayat as-salik fi nihe*yat al-masalik, n.d.; 22/3; No pagination. 25 lines.; 19 cm. (Box 8)
  Ref: GAL S II 5+2,1+2
- Dau' al-ma'ali li-bad' al-amali, n.d.; 22/4; No pagination. 17 lines. (Box 8)
  Ref: GAL S II 138.
  Here, Dau'al-amali.
- Unmudhaj al-labib fi khasa 'is al-habib, n.d.; 22/5; No pagination. 17 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 8)
  Ref: GAL S II 181, 27.
- Khususiyat yaum al-Jum'a wa-fadlihi 'ala ghairihi min sa'ir ayyam al-usbu, n.d.; 22/6; No pagination. 25 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 8)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi khassa hadhihi l-umma al-Muhammadiya."
- Risala fi al-mantiq, n.d.; 23; No pagination. 7 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 8)
  Ref: GAL S II 571 (?).
- [No further description available], 1060 H.; 24; 17 leaves. 27 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 8)
  Incipit: "tahdhib al-mantiq wal-kalam tawshihuhu bi-dhikr al-mufaddal al-min'am."
- at-Tabsira wat-tadhkira (fi ilm al-hadith), n.d.; 24; No pagination. 15 lines.; 17 cm. (Box 8)
  Incipit: "Yaqulu raji rabbihi l-muqtadir."
  Scribe: Muhammad Ahmad al-Halabi al- Bistami.
  Ref: GAL II 66.
- Kitab al-lata if, 1107 H (?).; 24; No pagination 21 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 8)
  Scribe: Muhammad Sadic al-Batrufi (?).
  Ref: GAL I 505 66.
- Sharh 'ara'is an-najib, 1232 H.; 25; 120 leaves (12 fasc.). 21 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 8)
  Incipit: "Subhan man 'ajuza 'an tasawwur kunhihi al- 'uqul."
- Muqaddima fi 'l-kalam 'ala 'l-basmala, 1113 H.; 26; No pagination. 19 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 13)
  Incipit: "Qala al-shaikh al0imam al- 'alim al-allama al- 'umda al-muhaqqiq al-fahhama."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Qasim ibn Muhammad.
- Taqrir al-qawanin al-mutadawila min 'ilm al-munazara (?), n.d.; 28; 10 leaves. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 13)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu ... yaqulu 'l-ba'is al-faqir Muhammad al-mar ashi l-mad'uww Bachaqlizade ..." (author).
  Ref: GAL I 418, SI 740, SII 498, NII 658.
- [No further description available], 1121 H.; 30; 20 leaves. 25 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 13)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi albasa ahn al-adab hulal al-mahaba."
  The work is a commentary on a certain qasida at the end of which there is a concise summary of the various metaphorica; conceits (3pp.).
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad ibn 'Abd al-Hayy al-Hanafi al-Qari.
- Risalat al-qaul al-ahamm fi tark al-hamm, 1306 H.; 31/1; 5pp. 18 lines.; 23 cm. (Box 13)
  Incipit: "Al-hamdu lillah lladhi ja ala l-faraj bish-shidda mawsulan."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As 'ad ibn Muhammad Naji al-'Aintabi.
  Ref: for author, GAL II 315.
- Ithaf as-siddiq bima yanfa 'uhu waqt ad-diq, 1306 H.; 31/2; 4.5pp. 18 lines.; 23 cm. (Box 13)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah wa-kafa wa-salam ala ibadihi lladhina staf."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As ad ibn Muhammad Naji al-'Aintabi.
- al-usul al-munifa lil-imam Abi Hanifa, 1113 H.; 33; 29 leaves. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 14)
  Incipit: "hamdan lillah kifa a ifdalihi."
  On title page of Manuscript: Bayad-Zadeh.
  Ref: GAL S II 647.
  In GAL: Bayadi.
- Sharh umm al-barahin (ar-risala as-sughra by Sanusi), n.d.; 34; 17 leaves. 21 lines. (Box 14)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi shahada bi-wujudihi jami' al-ka 'inat."
  Ref: for author, GAL 251, SII 345.
- al-minha fi s-sabha, 1306 H.; 35/1; 2.5pp. 18 lines.; 24 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah wa-kafa wa-salam ala 'ibadihi' alladhina stafa."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As'ad ibn Muhammad Naji _____ al-'Aintabi.
  Ref: GAL II 152, S II 191, 187.
- Tuhfat al-mujtahidim fi asma al-mujaddidin, n.d.[?].; 35/2; 1 p. 16 lines.; 24 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al- 'azim al-munna."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad as 'ad-al-Aintabi.
  Ref: GAL S II 190, 169 fff.
- al-kashf 'an mujawazat hadhihi al-umma' l-alf, 1306 H.; 35/3; 10.5pp. 18 lines.; 24 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah wa-kafa wa-salam ala 'ibadihi 'lladhina 'stafa."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As'ad al-Aintabi.
  Ref: GAL II 151, S II 187, 135.
- Qatf ath-thamar fi muwafaqat saiyidina 'Umar, 1306 H.; 35/4; 1.5pp. 16 lines.; 24 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah wa-salla' llah 'ala nabiyyihi' lledhi' jtabah."
  In rajaz.
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As 'ad al-Aintabi.
  Ref: GAL II 146, S II 180, 16.
- Risala fi ilm an-nafs, 1306 H.; 36; 11pp. 18 lines.; 23.5 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi la yakhibu min babihi amil."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad As 'ad ibn Muhammad Naji ____ al-'Aintabi.
  Ref: GAL SN II 673[?].
- Risala fi adab al-bahth, 1119 H.; 37; 47 leaves. 17 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "ya man waffaqana li-waza if al-bahth."
  Scribe[?]: Ali ibn Waliy (?).
  Ref: GAL S II 482.
  Here title reads: al-risala al-Husainiya fi fann al-adab (i Adab al-bahth).
- Nashr al-mahasin al- 'aliya fi fadl al-mashaayikh uli l-maqamat al- aliyya, 1087 H.; 39; 58 leaves. 25 lines. (Box 20)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah ... wa afdal as-salat wat-taslim 'ala sayyid al-mursalin."
  Scribe[?]: 'Abdalhayy ibn Abi Bakr ibn 'Ali ibn Muhammad al-Sulaimi.
  Ref: GAL II 177. S II 227.
- Risalat al-haqq al-wajib an-natiq bi-anna l-makhluq laisa 'aina l-khaliq, 1057 H.; 41; 38 leaves. 23 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi nasaba fi kull 'asr li-nasr ash-shari 'a al-Hanifiya al- 'ulama' a ..."
  Scribe[?]: Muhammad ibn Muhammad.
- al-Haskafi (Hisnkaifi), Abu l-Lutf al-Maqdisi Maqasid al-wasila, n.d.; 42; 32 leaves. 25 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "Hamdaan lillah 'adad(?) na 'ma 'ihi wash-shukr lahu 'ala tawali 'l-ayat."
  Ref: for author GAL S II 1021.
- Sharh al-urjuza al-Yasminiya, n.d.; 43/1; 6 leaves. 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi ahsa kulla shay'in 'adadan wa-ja 'ala 'l-awwal li-man a' ta wa'ttaqa."
  Ref: GAL I 471 S II 155.
- Risala fi 'ilm al-jabr wal-muqabala, nuqilat min kitab al-lubab fi sharh talkhis a mal al-hisab ... lish-sheik "Abdal aziz ibn Ali ibn Daud .., 43/2; 5 leaves. 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al- 'ala min wa-salla' llajh ala sayyidina Muhammad Khatim an-nabiyyin."
- Tuhfat al-ahbab fi'ilm al-hisab, 1083 H.; 43/3; 16 leaves. 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi sahhala' l-hisab wa-hawwana as-sa'ab."
  Place: al-Azhar, Egypt.
  Scribe[?]: _____ Ibn al-Hajj Qasim.
  Ref: GAL II 167 S II 215.
- al-usul wad-dawabit, n.d.; 44; 30 leaves. 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al- 'alamin wa-salla 'llah 'ala sayyidina Muhammad."
  Manuscript incomplete - end missing.
  The work deals with philosophical terminology.
- al-Shafa 'at al-saniyyat fi jami' al-bariyyat, 1207 H.; 45; 12 leaves. 15 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 12)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi ja 'alana min ummat shafi' al-umam."
- Bayan al-ma 'ani fi sharh aqidat ash-Shaiban, 1199 H.; 46; No pagination. 21 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 11)
  Incipit: "Qala sayyiduna wa-mawlana wa-shaikhuna wa-imamuna ..."
  Scribe: Muhammad Amin ibn 'Abdallah.
  Ref: GAL S II 461.
- Sharh maqamat al-Hariti, n.d.; 47; 95 leaves. & 2 more leaves in a different handwriting. 23 lines.; 20,5 cm. (Box 11)
  qala al-shaikh al-imam al-alim ... 'Abdallah ibn al-Husain ibn 'Abdallah al-Ukbari."
  Ref: GAL I 20,25,88, 93, 114, 247, 277, 282. SI 40, 54, 142, 192, 488, 495, 510.
- Kitab sina at al-muntahi sharh bida 'at al-mubtadi, 957 H.; 48; No pagination. 20 lines.; 17 cm. (Box 11)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al- alamin was-salat 'ala sayyid al-anam wal- alamin."
  Ref: GAL S I 793.
  Here, Bali khalifat as-Sufiyya.
- Cahr al-milla al-kufriya bil-adilla al-Muhammadiya li-takhrib dair al-mahalla al-Jawwaniya, 1151 H.; 49; 20 cm. No pagination. 21 lines. (Box 11)
  Incipit[?]: "al-Hamdu lillah alladhi a'azza 'l-islam wa-ahlahu."
  Scribe[?]: Umar al-Badrawi.
  Ref: GAL II 313.
- Mawazin al-casoro*n min al-rijal, or, Mawazin al-rijal al-Qasirin, n.d.; 50; No pagination. 31 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 11)
  Incipit[?]: "al Hamdu lillah rabb al-alamin was-salat wat-tas-lim'ala ashraf al-murasalin."
  Ref: GAL S II 464.
  For work 46517.
- al-Bishara bi-fadl as-saltana wal-wizara, n.d.; 52; 15 leaves. 21 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 11)
  Incipit[?]: "qala al-abd al-faqir ila 'llah ta ala Mar i ibn Yusuf al-Hanbali al-Maqdisi."
  Manuscript is incomplete.
  Ref: for author GAL II 103, 369, S II 496.
- 'Umdat al-kuttib wa- 'uddat dhawi 'l-albab, 1162 H.; 53; No pagination. 15 lines.; 16 cm. (Box 11)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-mun im al-mifdal al-kabir al-mit al" (muta ali).
  Ref: For author, S I 434.
- al-Jawhara al-munifa fi sharh wasiyat Abi Hanifa, 1130 H.; 55/1; No pagination. 17 lines.; 16 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-mutawahhid bi-wujub al-wujud wal-baqa."
  Ref: For author see GAL S II 354, 646.
- Kitab ta'allum al-fara'id, 1133 H.; 55/2; No pagination. 9 lines.; 16 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al-'alamin wal-'aqibat lil-muttaqin."
  The work is a commentary on al-figh al-akbar by Abu Hanifa.
  At the top of the first page the Manuscript reads: "Hatha kitab ta'allum al-fara'id."
  It seems, however, that the work is Risala fi l-fara'id by piri-ade (GAL S II 647).
  At the end of this work here is only the first page of another work (third in the volume) probably another commentary on al-figh al-akbar.
- 'Iqd al-jawhar ath-thamin fi adh-dhikr wa-turuq al-ilbas wat-talqin, 1223 H.; 56; No pagination. 25 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rafi' manshur wilayatihi."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Ahmad al-Harawi.
  Ref: GAL S II 399.
  Here, al- 'Iqd al-mukallal bil-jawhar ath-thamin fi dh-dhikr...
- As-sabiyyat fi mawa 'iz al-bariyyaat, n.d.; 57; No pagination. 21 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-malik al-jabba4 al-aziz al-qahhar."
  Ref: GAL S II 583.
- Risalat at-tathbit 'inda at-tabyit, 1306 H.; 59; 12pp. 16 lines.; 20 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah 'ala l-Islam wash-shukr lillah ala 'l-in 'am."
  The risala is written in rhyming couplets divided into chapters bearing such titles as: "wujub al-iman bis-su' al," "hikmat as-su'al," "ikhtisas as-su' al bi-hadhini al-umma."
  Scribe: Muhammad As 'ad al-Aintabi.
- Ghibtat an-nazir fi tarjamet ash-shaikh 'Abd al-Qadir, n.d.; 60; No pagination. 15 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-qadir 'ala tasrif muradihi fi tashrif ahl widadihi."
  Incomplete; the end is missing.
  Ref: GAL S II 75.
- Kitab al-Quduri fi'l-figh. 723 H.(?) Scribe: Ahmad ibn Muhammad al-Mutatabbib., 61; No pagination. 15 lines.; 24 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "Kitab at-tahara qala'llah ta ala ya ayyuha 'lladhina amanu."
- Diwan Sultan al-Ushshaq, 961 H.; 62; No pagination. 16 lines.; 17 cm. (Box 15)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi khtassa habibahu."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Ali al-Shafi.
  Ref: GAL I 262, S I 462.
- [No further description available], 1037 H.; 63; No pagination. 17 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: Missing
  The first page(s) missing.
  Scribe: al-Hajj Muhammad ibn Zakariya.
  Ref: for Ushnuhiya see GAL S I 674.
- Jam' al-asrar fi ma ani al-ashrar aw at-ta n fi as-sufiyya al-akhyar, 1283 H.; 64/1; 36 leaves. 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Scribe: Husain al-Mawlawi al-Humsi.
  Ref: GAL S II 473 17
- Ijaza ... 'an 'Abd al-Ghani an-Nabuluzi, 1123 H.; 64/2; 42 leaves. 19 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi rafa'a aqdar ahl-al-'ilm."
  The Ijaza is apparently of jam' al-asrar.
  Scribe: 'Abdallah ibn Salim ibn Muhammad ibn Salim ibn 'Isa al-Basri.
  Ref: For author. GAL SN II 478.
- Sharh al-'awamil al-mi' a, 1132 H.; 64/2; No pagination. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "Tawajjahna ila janabika wa-qasadna nahwa babika."
  Scribe: 'Ali ibn Mustafa.
  Ref: GAL S II 630.
- Ijaza, 1168 H.; 64/3; 6pp. (40-45) 19 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipt: al-hamdu lillah wa-kafa wa-salam 'ala 'ibadihi 'Iladhina satafa."
  The Ijaza is apparantly that of jam' al-asrar by Nabulusi.
  Scribe: 'Abd al-mu'ti ibn al-Hajj Ahmad Zawin(?).
  Ref. For author, GAL II 327, GAL S II 455.
- Risalat suluk salik al-mawlawiyaw a-nusuk nasik as-Sufiya, n.d.; 64/5; 25 leaves. (57-81) 17 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah hamdan yaliqu bijanabihi."
- [No further description available], n.d.; 64/6; 11 leaves. 14 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu, lillah rabb al- alamin wa-salle illah ala sayyidina wa-mawlana Muhammad."
  A Sufic work.
  Colophon missing.
- Thabt 'Abt al-Karim ash-Sharabati, 1168 H.; 64/7; 5 leaves. (100-104). 19 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah hamdu man wasala man inqata 'e ilaihi bi-ihsanihi."
  Scribe: Abd al Mu ti ibn al-Hajj Ahmad Zawin.
  Ref: for author, GAL SN II 478[?].
- al-Anwar al-lam iyya fi tariqat as-sadat an-Naqshabandiyya, 64/10; 9 leaves. (129-130). 25 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "Al-hamdu lillah ... i lam waffaqaka llah ta ala."
- Risalat as-sirat as sawiy shrh dibajat al-mathnawiy, 1281 H.; 64/11; 38 leaves. (139-176). 17 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi sharadha dhatahu bi-dhatihi."
  Scribe: Husain Haqqi al-Mawlawi.
- Risalat daf' al-iham wa-raf' al-ibham, 1283 H.; 64/12; 10 leaves. (186-195). 21 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah al-mulhim al-haqq."
  Scribe: Hussai ____ Haqqi al- Mawlawi.
- Tarji' al-atyar bi-muraqqis al-ash 'ar, n.d.; 65; No pagination. 26 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "Qala' l-qadi 'l-allama wahidu 'd-din 'Abdarrahman ibn Yahya al-Anisi."
  Collected by the author's son, Muhammad ivn Abc al-Rahman.
  Ref: GAL SII, 817.
- Sharh al-ajurrumiya (al-muqaddima alajurrumiya), 1145 H.; 66; No pagination. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al- 'alamin wa-ma tawfiqi illa billah..."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Ahmad al-Rustumi .. al-Shafi i.
- (Mukhtasar) al-Hashiya ala sharh qawa' id al-i'rab, 1118 H.; 67/1; No pagination. 23 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "vaqulu al-'abd al-faqir ila rahmat maulahu al-ghaniy al-qawily Muhammad ibn Abdarrahman al-Hamawiy."
  The work commented upon in this Hasiva is apparently Muwassi at-tullab ila qawa' al-i'rab by Zainaddin halid ibn' Abdallah ibn Abi Bakr al-Azhari (GAL II 27). It is not clear, however, from the incipit whether by "sharh" is meant a certain commentary the author of which is not mentioned here, or Muwassil at-tullab itself.
  The title page reads: "Hashiyat ala sharh a qawa id lish-shaikh... Muhammad ibn Abdarrman al-Hamawi."
  The incipit, on the other hand reads: "Maqulu... al- abd al-faqir... Muhammad ibn Abderrahman al-Hamawi... faqad sa'alani ba'du l-ikhwan... an akhtasira hashiyata shaikhi wa-ustadhi... ash-shaikh Abi Bakr Shunwan*i 'ala sharh qawa id al-i rab lish-s... khalid al-Azhari..."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn ash-Shaikh Ahmad al-Mutatabbib (Aleppo).
- Kitab ma rawahu al-wa'un fi akhbar at-ta'un, n.d.; 68/1; No pagination. 21 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah mu'addid al-arzaq."
  Ref: GAL II 146, S II 182, 32.
- al-Wadik fi fudl ad-din, 1136 H.; 68/2; No pagination. 32 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah ws salat was salam 'ala rusul Allah."
  Scribe: Muhammad ibn Muhammad al-Barwawi.
  Ref: GAL II 155, S II 193, 245.
- Kitab buluah al-amal, 1138 H.; 68/3; No pagination. 21 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "kitab bulugh al-amal fihi al-mu 'arae war-radd ala l-firag wa-ahl ad-da awi..."
- al-Kashf'an mujawazat hadhihi al-umma al-alf, 1138 H. (?).; 68/4; 1 leaf. 20 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah rabb al-alamin."
  First leaf only.
  Ref: GAL II 151. S II 187,135
- al-Jami al-khair, date: illegible.; 69; No pagination. 22 lines.; 25 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "Bab kaifa kana bad' u l-Gahyi."
  Scribe: illegible.
- Sharh al-burda, 1029 H.; 70; No pagination. 21 lines.; 20.5 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit[?]: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi ja 'ala maqadir al- 'ulama(?) ..."
  Scribe: Isma il ibn Isa.
- [No further description available], n.d.; 73; No pagination. 20 lines.; 34 cm. (Box 10)
  A voluminous Manuscript which is a commentary written in the style of a pamphlet, using the formula "fa- in qulta ... qultu."
  From the introduction one can gather that the commentary is written in the light of the sciences of balagha and ma ani.
- Fatawi, 1139 H.; 74/1; 100 leaves. 29 lines.; 22 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah alladhi yu 'ti al-hikma man yasha u."
- Majma' al-muntakhabat, n.d.; 75; No pagination. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 10)
  Incipit: "al-hamdu lillah kashif zalam az-zulm."
  Ref: GAL S II 956, 89.
- Jami' al-fatawi, 972 H.; 76; No pagination. 19 lines.; 21 cm. (Box 6)
  Incipit: Missing.
  The beginning is missing.
  Scribe: 'Abd al-Mu ti ibn 'Abd al- Ghaffar ibn Ibrahim.
- ar-Rasa 'il az-Zainiya fi 'l-masa il al- Hanafiya, n.d.; 76/2; 91 leaves. No. of lines varies.; 22 cm. (Box 17)
  Incipit: "Subhan al-munazzih 'an al-ashbah wan-naza' ir."
  Ref: GAL S II 426, 27.
- Rawdat al-'ulama 'wa-nuzhat al-fudalaa, 1275 H.; 77; 172 leaves (numbered). 23 lines.; 19.5 cm. (Box 17)
  Incipit[?]: "al-Hamdu lillah al-Karim... was-salat ala nabiyih."